So uh, let's start where we uh.
Left on Monday. Oh, by the way,
announcement that we're about to drop in
the material section of the team.
The first notes generated Andrea
yesterday reviewed them and me too.
So now.
Will share that is AI generated content
from the transcript of the of the class.
It's not just the the generation I
developed the GPT.
It does the job,
but actually in several cases I read the
output and said expand this,
use that and so it's not just the
generation.
Or include reference to this,
include this example or this stuff.
So it is part of experiment of this
course and in any case you will get notes
at the end of the course with all the
things this is not.
Even though it contains most of the
things that we say and even more
information,
does not replace a chapter of the book
and pragmatics programming language
pragmatics.
Will still be important, but again,
when this master course and not an
undergraduate course,
please spend your time in becoming a
better programmer,
not just learning things to pass the exam,
because at the end of the day the goal is
that you you become a very.
OK, so.
Um.
We left with the compilers, etcetera. OK,
we had this quick review of the
whitespace compiler, just as an example,
small enough to be browsed in a few
minutes.
But still containing all the main
elements of of the language pipeline.
Now basically we finished the the quick
review of the main constituent of a
programming language.
Now we start talking about.
New areas.
Today we start talking about the
importance of names in in programs.
Names are the most important thing.
It is often overlooked both for
documentation, software engineering,
security, I mean names.
Uh, are basically the contractor.
Between us programmers and the machine,
and so understanding the names is a
crucial part of the programming and I.
I'd like to remind you that names are not
necessarily the name of the variables
you're using,
or the name of the functions.
So in a grammar that would have been the
production of the identifier.
Or the literal names are also pointers in
AC programming language.
If you have the pointer,
you can refer to the object referred by
the pointer thanks to the operation that
a compiler give you.
To reference a different object using
that number.
So in in a in a sense also a point that
is a name.
So the name is not necessarily the the
the literal, but is a.
Crucial element to define the
organization in the memory of a
programming language. So we will start.
With the scoping again,
sorry this you may already know enough,
but so we review quickly scoping we
discuss briefly.
Again,
lexical closure that I really quickly,
quickly introduced in the very first
class,
but we will spend some more time in
understanding the true nature of the.
Of the lexical closures and and then we
start moving on to the memory management
because names typically refers to also to
memory object, not only to memory object,
names also refer to classes.
Which is not technically memory object,
but most of the names refer to actual
values that are stored in the in the in
the memory and the the the scoping rules
that govern the visibility of names.
It's inevitable that they affect the
lifetime of the objects in in the memory
of a of a programming language and and
that is a big, big, big, big, big, big,
big topic because 80% of the time.
In programming is managing memory and as
I pointed out in the in the introduction
and now we have easily one terabyte of
RAM on a system and you still have
pointers.
If you are using your PC you have a TB.
And database, file system, security, etc.
So as a programmer,
we're still managing with very simple
tools,
more and more RAM and then there are
consideration about the.
Performance, which is crucial.
So you always have to understand where
the memory lies in the runtime of your
programming language.
So we start this journey now.
At some point we will start digging down
and we will see how.
Objects and memory layouts are
implemented in a virtual machine such as
Java Vito machine or the common language
runtime so that you can see.
All the costs that you have to sustain
when you make a virtual call or not,
what is the cost of the garbage
collection and various approaches you can
add to?
Automatically manage the memory and so on.
So this today we start this journey and
and we move over the traditional compiler
stuff, so.
Just to as a bridge,
let me hook into the C#.
Compiler. OK,
so now it is an open source project.
So you go on GitHub, you look for Roslin.
The name of the the system is Roslin.
Roslin is a modular.
Compiler architecture that compiles
multiple programming language targeting
the.net by code. OK,
so it is also interesting to have a look
at a real world.
System for this reason.
So name starts with the name of the files,
which typically is not part of the
program, the of your program or.
Not not entirely in Java,
you know that every file dot Java should
be named after the class the file
contains.
So there are examples of programming
languages in which you have some rules
that impose you the name of the file. OK.
And in that case,
the name of the file is part of the
program.
But even though even if it's not like
this,
so in C the tradition is you name your
file as you like, not my problem,
the C compiler will work anyway.
Names are important because it's the way
you browse the code you don't know.
So the ability to look for names is not
just understand where the name is
available or which is the particular
variable you're about to refer or memory
location, but it's.
Also a way to browse a large code base
and there are a lot of naming conventions.
So let's start with the naming convention.
Notice that naming convention are a
convention.
I mean there is no mandatory rule in the
programming.
Language that mandates you to use
uppercase, lowercase, et cetera.
There are two main naming convention
typically for variable classes,
name of classes, et cetera that are.
So when you type in the the name of your
method,
you will start with the lowercase or
uppercase name.
OK,
you're using the camel notation and it is
called camel because if you look at the
camel you start low and you go high.
OK and.
And there is also an alternative that is
you start with the upper case,
that's the Pascal notation and and it's
the one used that by by.net.
I think so as you can see the main in C#
in in Java would would have been a lower
case main and here is uppercase main.
All these conventions are crucial because
it helps you browse the code and in fact
there are automatic tool.
Since ages,
there are automatic tools that checks
this convention that are part of the
pragmatics of the language,
so the set of conventions we use to help
us understanding a programme.
And and nowadays these are also enforced
by the AI. So if you use a copilot,
I mean if you use Visual Studio Code,
it is likely that you've been asked to
activate copilot. copilot is an AI.
Which basically see what you type and
helps you complete the line.
And if you pay attention,
if you pick up a language,
you will start seeing names that are the
convention,
the conventional in the conventional form
of the names of that particular language.
So first of all, names,
even before becoming objects of
discussion about the semantics of the
name in a program text,
names are a crucial element to understand
a program and you must be become pay
attention.
To the use of the names.
Because if you write the program,
you have to pay attention to use names
that someone else can read.
But you're about to read more than write,
so you have to pay attention.
And you may think this is a trivial
statement. It's not because.
If I ask you to understand how the C#
compiler works,
I'm pretty sure that all of you would
have browsed to the C CSC directory.
CSC is the name of the C# compiler,
so that's the tool.
And and you will have a look for the main
as I just did the program and you will
have started reading the code as an
interpreter, a human interpreter.
You pretend to know the semantics of the
language and say OK main.
And say OK, I have to find this main core.
Now all the tools GitHub included helps
you browse the code.
So on the right I can find the main core.
Method and and I understand that there is
a some logger.
And uh, and then there is a big client.
And these big client has a huge set of
arguments that I unlikely.
It's unlikely that I fully understand and
and then there is a.
A run uh.
Static method that is used.
This run is this define some external
code that that will be that will invoke
this this this common line.
So this is a typical if you're feeling
that you're not getting what it's doing.
The norm.
No real world program as a main in which
you have ask input, ask input,
process the input, print the output.
That was the 70s, the 80s,
maybe even the 90s. Nowadays it's not.
If you take a graphical application you
will have the event loop.
So you will have a pick a message from
the pick an event from the event queue.
So the graphical system basically handles
all the interrupts of the mouse and the
keyboard, generates events, queue them.
In the window queue and then you pick,
you switch the particular event you
received and you perform some code. OK,
so basically you are writing a program
which reacts to external events and this
is the habit also in less.
Event-oriented PROGRAMMING nowadays,
and this is the proof.
I mean here you see just a run because
there is some other part of a huge
program which will use techniques that we
will explore during this course such as
reflection.
And so the ability of a of a running
program program to inspect other binary
code and invoke dynamically its abilities
without.
Determine statically the behaviour of the
program. And so in in this context,
as you can see,
it's difficult to go and browse the the
main and say OK, this is.
The behavior of this program,
so in your opinion.
Where should I look for?
Now that I have the C# compiler.
As a program.
And.
A number of all this where you will look.
Let's let's look for the parser.
One look for any CPU.
Not interesting. Then you move to arm 64.
Not interesting.
Oh, so this is the full C compiler.
It's not clearly.
If you go back to the C# folder.
You may notice that there are other
folders and you may think you know what,
maybe CSC is just the executable
definition and maybe there is a lot of
code somewhere else that is invoked
indirectly by those few lines and you
know.
The analyzer driver.
Seems provided. Uh, promising.
Unfortunately, it's not in here.
Let's look at the ortable.
Now looks much better. OK,
so you see names how much are important
because one may wonder why the C#
compiler is in the portable folder and
not in the compiler form.
And sometimes it's just because of a
history,
because every programmer feels the
frustration of the empty file and you
have to type in a name,
and the name is the first one.
It came to your mind in that particular
moment, and that may last 20 years or.
Everybody else, because you are that day.
In fact,
the first day in 2001 I started working
on the C and.net runtime in Microsoft.
The first thing that I did when I check
out the full runtime.
It was opening the object file.
I was curious to see object class
implementation because typically that is
binary. So there are easy thing.
Now you see the names and the names
include the parser.
And and there is an abstract lecture
which is an interesting name helps us to
understand that that is involved in the
first part of compiling and then there is
the I don't know the lecture.
Let's have a look at quick look at the
Lexer and as you can see the the Lexer as
a mode that is a typical.
We didn't discuss much,
but honestly we don't have much time for
that, but.
You may know from previous studies that
some languages have preprocessors.
Preprocessors basically allows you to
transform the program with the program
before.
The compiler to transform.
I don't know macro definition in C OK,
so the macro definition in C is just that
whenever you find the sequence exploding
that and then compile.
OK and and C for instance has a
preprocessor itself,
so you have a hash something.
It's available in the language and so the
lexer as a mode and several modes because
sometimes you may wanna read XML dot
comments or XML element tags etc.
So basically depending on the mode,
the way the tokenizer will tokenize.
And I think that will change. OK, so.
And there are several modes of this.
And then oh,
like in the white space compiler,
there is a token info because when when
you tokenize you have to emit a token
data structure with some information
about the token so that if you parse it
the the name of a variable you don't just
need the.
The information that that is name of a
variable token.
You also want the text of the name of the
variables,
otherwise you won't be able to compile
things. OK, and so as you can see,
the ideas are very similar.
The code is much more complicated because
the PROGRAMMING language is much more
complicated, but.
Nonetheless,
a lots of switch case because we learned
that the lexer is an automata and the
automata is naturally implemented as a
for loop, which say OK,
if I'm in this state I behave like this,
if I'm in that state I behave like that.
And so on. OK and then syntax kind,
numerical literal token info value kind
if it's a system in 22 then.
Literal.
So you have to parse a literal and return
a token of value literal of type in 32
and in the token info you will get all
the necessary information. OK so.
Two things if you're curious and I I will
encourage you to go and try to understand
where is.
You can see there is also the language
parser. Go and browse.
I will put in the theme of the course the
link to the repo.
Try to understand the strategy in the
parsing of the compiler and look around
because you will learn a lot in the way
this code now has 20 years,
no more than that.
It does.
96.
30 years, almost.
So it's a time machine.
It has been mostly rewritten since the
original implementation. Nevertheless,
the root and some of the names are still
rooted in there. OK, and as you can see,
you will find patterns that we just
discussed.
OK, so on one hand,
I hope this convinced you that even real
world code is organised the way Andrea
has shown in by the mean of formal
methods or I did show it by the mean of
the.
White space compiler. In any case,
that is the theory and still backs the
implementation of this thing.
Let's go back to names. So names,
understanding names in the context of a
complicated program, it's important.
It's important first,
because if you invoke a method of
function,
you have to find the definition of that
function and that is not always easy. Why?
You've seen the run method.
The run method,
technically it's not a method or or an
element of a class, it's a function.
So starting.
I would say from Java.
Um.
Mid 90s PCs were efficient enough to
support as a mainstream the notion of a
function as values in program in programs
OK.
So what does it means if you take uh?
C,
Pascal and many other mainstream
languages of those years.
Basic functions or map or procedures were
basically declarations.
Which allow to name a sequence of
instruction in the program. OK,
that is a function.
But uh.
It wasn't fully possible to treat those
function that are basically fragments of
code as values,
so it wasn't possible to assign to a
variable a function and then use that
variable to invoke the function.
OK, so that was pre-java.
With Java mostly thanks to the interface
that we will discuss when we will talk
about types, it was possible.
To pass around your program functions,
it was a little bit clumsy in the syntax
with respect to ML,
Camel and Askel and other functional
languages,
but nevertheless in the mainstream.
The functional programming pattern,
so the ability to pass a function as an
argument to another function became an
habit. OK.
O Let me go back to the C Shar compiler.
So finding.
This run where it is.
It's not that easy because it may be a
direct call to a declared function,
but you you may are invoking.
A variable which contains the reference
to a function. OK,
so understanding this the the names,
it's crucial because sometimes you get
you start browsing the code and you get
stuck in some point because you see.
Invoke this name,
but that is not the name of the function.
That is the name of the variable that has
been ***** by through dozens of of calls
and you received some.
Lambda as we will call it today that has
been inserted somewhere as in the program.
So OK,
so the strategy when you read the the the
program,
you have to pay a lot of attention to the
meaning of every single.
Name you find because it may not be what
you may think of. It doesn't.
It may not be true that since I'm
applying,
so I apply arguments to to the name.
That means that that is a static method.
It may be a variable that Java introduced
it in the form of interfaces.
net refined the notion and introduced the
notion of delegates.
Mind this word because delegates affected
the the evolution of programming language
since then.
So delegates basically are values.
Are pairs,
so are objects that are provided you by
the runtime and are basically a pair with
two arguments. One is the this pointer.
And the other is the pointer to the
function that you want to invoke.
And why you need this pointer?
Because if you if you want to pass around
not a function but a method,
then you having the pointer to the to the
to the definition of the method is not
enough.
You need also that this argument which is
the particular object on which you want
to invoke.
The the function and so the delegate
basically is the pair and introduced the
in in in C# the ability to pass around
the methods as values.
OK,
it was a way to encapsulate all the
information needed to to invoke the the
the method dynamically. Why it is useful?
Imagine.
As a computer scientist,
we have really the fantasy.
Imagine a sorting algorithm.
So same collection and and different
algorithm for sorting and then you can
say sort you pass the algorithms as a
first argument and the second argument
the the collection to be ordered and.
The in in the body you will apply the
function to the argument. OK,
so that that's the typical pattern.
Not really compelling,
but it that that is OK.
So I hope by now to have convinced you
that names are the most important thing
of a program.
Of a program because basically they
convey the intention of the programmer
because file not found exception as you
there is an exception because the file
has not been found. OK, but that is an A.
The programmer could have been invoked,
my personal exception number one,
and the program would have worked anyway.
You may if you try to crack it some
website code,
you may know this by art because since
JavaScript is not really compiled,
there are a lot of obfuscator that
basically play.
On this and basically strips of the
program from all the elements to make it
readable and rename all the variables of
the program so that you have to struggle
to understand what that particular
JavaScript function does. OK,
this form of obfuscation is just.
The application of the fact that you can
perfectly preserve the the the machine
semantics of a program by renaming all
the the the names in in the in the
program with totally different names,
even meaning meaningless and it will work
anyway so.
The intention of the program is part of a
name, and that's an important part.
The second part that is important is.
Where the meaning of that name has been
defined in the program.
And that is bound to a number of
mechanisms. So technically,
by saying that scoping is the only
mechanism, it's untrue.
Because.
Do you think that this file not found
exception is the name I'm interested in?
No, no.
It will be probably system dot IO dot
find no.
Found exception because when you manage a
program,
names are really important and we got
thousands of names.
So at some point we said OK,
let's introduce some mechanism to.
Have very long names so that we don't
collide in having names.
And you know what?
Having very long names is really
uncomfortable when you type in.
So someone said OK, let's use a trick,
let's use the dot.
Technically that is a name. OK,
system dot IO dot.
File not found exception is a name,
but we give a little bit of semantics.
So in the rules in which the programming
language gives name meaning to name,
technically we're not looking at the name
itself, but we also.
Try to look for that name in namespaces.
OK,
so the scoping of a name in a program is
basically defines where that particular
name is visible.
And how that names relates to its
definition.
That is the core notion of names in a
program, the declaration.
So now there are two types of scoping.
So if I look here,
I don't know either message. Am I sure?
Can I say where?
This value where it lies by looking at X
of the program.
Why?
So there are two kinds of scoping,
static scoping and dynamic scoping.
And which is the difference?
In dynamic scoping,
it's the execution which defines the
actual value that will be bound to a name.
That is correct and.
It's essential that you get that.
Almost all the program modern programming
language are using static scoping.
With some exceptions.
So,
and it's not just an exception in the in
the programming language.
The exception may be in a.
Given.
Word in the programming language.
So before going there,
so then I'm scoping that it's just the
name E is available in all the program
depending.
The last one who assigned the name E will
define the which is the name E this form
of typically this is easy to implement in
the.
In the programming language you have a
table with all the names. You go,
you find the last version of the name,
you look for the value. That's it. OK,
so I mean dynamic scoping at the
beginning was just because it was the
easy way to give meaning to to names.
That's it. So static scope.
Copping as this important element that
you have to be able to understand the
value the name refers to just by looking
at the text of the program,
so without having to wait for the runtime.
And this has a lot of implications.
That I want to draw your attention to
because when the name E in this method
appears,
I know that I have to find some
declaration. In this case is the cache.
Let me go back.
Go back.
To a more interesting.
Parser.
Let's take a more interesting piece of
code to comment some method. OK,
so this is the constructor.
So where is this?
Where is this how under under score
options?
Where is the where I should I look for
for that under score options?
Where you why? I mean you're right, OK.
under score is a convention.
Thank you for underlying this.
So this particular set of programmers
decide that to help programmers reading
and finding easily what is a field and
distinguish fields from.
Variables.
They decide to use under score as the
first character,
but I could have written all options and
would have been the same.
What is the real reason?
Because I know that it's a field
assignment and not a variable assignment.
That is one reason I look for the
arguments,
the formal parameters of my method,
and I find that there is no declaration
there.
So basically I'm starting to say OK,
here there is no var.
Or type to declare.
So that is not a declaration,
it's an assignment. If it's an assignment,
the declaration should be somewhere else
because I know that the grammar of the
language has a tree structure.
I start browsing the abstract syntax tree.
So I'm not going linearly looking for
that name because I know that in the
grammar the constructor should lie of a
class, should lie in a class declaration,
and that is a scope.
And so I I know that the names are
hierarchically defined in the text in the
program definition,
and so under score options is not defined
inside locally to this particular method
with that is the constructor,
so it should be declared.
At the uer layer, which is in the class.
OK, let's go for the class.
And in this case, of course,
we will find it hoefully.
I love it. No, it's there, unfortunately.
OK, I found the decoration.
Which is market read only.
But I did assign it.
We will see later to that. OK,
so under score options.
We found that and so.
By knowing the scoping rules,
which says basically there are code
blocks.
Code blocks contains local variables that
can be declared locally.
Then you have the scope of the class.
If the PROGRAMMING language supports
classes,
in that case I have also to look in the
environment of the classes,
so the declaration in the class which we
call fields and if I fail to find there.
Where where I should go?
Global. OK,
so there is a basically an hierarchy of
allocations that are bound to the grammar
of the language.
That is one of the reason because you
really have to understand the grammar of
the language because the grammar.
Number of the language defines the scope.
That's important.
Now I'm not.
I'm not sure I will be so lucky.
O.
Question.
Let me make an an hypothesis because I
would have to scrub and scrape and find
some place.
Suppose that I went to under score
options and I didn't find the line this
line.
Suppose it's not here.
Am I allowed to think that is a global
variable?
Why?
Might maybe part of us.
Perfect.
Your colleague notice that there is a.
This partial that may hint that this
particular class is not entirely defined
in this file,
and so maybe the field declaration is not
in this file,
but it's in another file because this
particular PROGRAMMING language supports.
Of course,
a partial definition of classes,
and basically the compiler joins all the
text of the partial in a single block and
then parse the full class. OK,
so the definition is incomplete.
And so I have to go and check also that
so as you can see.
The scoping of a name in a real world
PROGRAMMING language can be pretty
daunting. It's not trivial,
it's not just the local variable.
But nevertheless,
the advantage and the force you have in
your hand is that you know the rules.
So if you understand the grammar of the
language,
you know how to browse the syntax tree.
That you clearly see.
Actually we invent things because it
allows us us to see the tree OK and find
the right definition. OK now.
The the scoping of a name has
implications in the execution of the
program.
Question, so let me.
Simplify our life a little bit.
Oh.
I'm improvising A syntax.
I think I know the the language, but.
Uh.
I'm pretty sure that you wrote this
example so many times since the first
year. That's just what.
Um.
I use the this ref because the name is
not defined only by the name or the type,
but also from a number of qualifiers.
In this case, for instance, I say OK,
I'm asking.
To the caller of this swap function to
pass something that is a reference,
so it can be the result of an expression
because I want to sign.
I want to change the value outside of of
the scope. OK, but we will.
Review this thing. I mean,
I'm pretty sure you you're familiar with
the mechanism.
What I'm trying to do today is to force
you to reason about simple things. OK,
so if you were expecting me to tell you
very complicated stuff, no, I mean.
Being an ADVANCED PROGRAMMING is first of
all having a full understanding of the
nuance of a language of a very subtle
difference in very few characters,
and I appreciate the difference because
that is where typically the problem lies.
OK, so.
I said OK, I have the TMP variable,
the TMP variable that's been this
declaration say OK,
there is a name TMP which is a variable
the system easily.
Can prove that is of type int,
so I could have written of course int.
TMP would have been the same thing.
And the initial value is a. OK,
we know all this.
So what if you were the compiler?
Tyler,
what you can What can you tell about the
TMP name? That that name,
because of the scoping rules,
is accessible only.
That's important because clearly you can
implement a very stupid PROGRAMMING
language which allocates allocation in
the memory with the TMP slot and keep
this allocated for all the execution of
the program would have been valid.
So first of all,
keep your mind in your mind that that
would have been a valid program
implementation. So there's not,
it's not written with some difference,
but then you can.
Have uh the allocation which outlast in
the memory.
The and in fact there are PROGRAMMING
languages that are implemented like this.
Very simple interpreter that may become
even popular languages started in with
very stupid implementation. For instance,
Perl has no arguments.
They pass an array all around the code
and the argument is all the arguments of
the function are in fact an array that is
passed around passed around the program.
So don't expect that it's always true
that TMP would have been deallocated.
At the end of the execution above,
that is an optimization.
You may say you know what I I'm.
I can allocate the.
The variable TMP only during the
execution.
This has a lot of interesting properties.
For instance,
if I allow recursive calls and I need
multiple TM PS that will be supported,
but apart from that I can.
I I can prove given the semantics of my
language that TMP can be allocated when I
enter swap and I can be it can be
deallocated when I exit the swap function.
Pretty obvious implication.
We started with the semantic of a name,
the scoping of a name,
and we ended up talking about the
implementation.
So the scoping rules of a PROGRAMMING
language.
Will define the typical, reasonable,
efficient implementation of that language,
OK,
and the data structure that are needed to
implement that language.
And this brings us to.
An important part of our future classes,
which is the allocation of the memory,
but.
This is not the only effect that the
scoping rules introduced in a PROGRAMMING
language.
Another important effect is the one we
already briefly mentioned, which is.
Possible if we allow to define.
Function as a value.
So basically you can return a function as
a result of the invocation of a function.
Usually those languages are called high
order languages because in fact the
function is called is a program.
So basically you have a function.
Which is a program which return a portion
of a program,
and so the program somehow talks about
itself. OK,
it's capable of not managing values,
but also managing functions.
OK.
There are several views of this this
thing, but nevertheless so.
Let me refine the quick example that and
discuss the quick example we had at the
very beginning.
Let's see.
Counter.
Uh, var N equal 0.
Return.
Function.
Um.
Return.
And plus.
So I define a function which returns a
function.
And we already commented,
so I don't want to go too long.
I already posed the questions.
I can have C1 counter and then if I call
C1 this will print out zero,
C1 again it will print out one.
And if I say var C2 equal counter C2 will
print out zero OK.
Why?
Because of the scoping rules of the
language.
Because if you want to give the proper
meaning to this very small fragment of
code in this function.
I'm using the scope and we are in static
scoping and static scoping impose us to
let access to the names that are defining
in all the scope in which I am included.
So this function is included in another
function, so it should be it should.
Have access to the local variable of that
function and maybe to the global if it's
a method to the fields,
if it otherwise to the global environment.
OK,
so when you allow for nested definition
of functions then you have to consider
all the values that are accessible.
When at the definition place available to
that particular code.
So this variable N should should be bound
here exactly for the same reasons the
under score option variable was bound to
the field. OK,
so it's not declared inside the file.
Function, which is an anonymous function,
so it has not a name,
but it's a value and this name.
Since it's not declared inside,
it should be in the outside scope which
is the function counter.
And this name is a local variable now.
When you invoke the counter function,
you return a function.
This function which I highlight and it's
this increment.
This function we said that the N the N
variable will be not needed anymore when
you exit the function,
but we just returned a value which
depends on that particular.
Name.
So lexical closures are basically a
result of the scoping rules of the
PROGRAMMING language,
and they are needed to preserve a
reasonable semantics of the PROGRAMMING
language,
because otherwise this code will not have
a meaning without this mechanism.
So basically.
By returning the function which depends
on the local variable N,
I'm extending the lifespan of that name N
until the function.
Is valid.
This is an I I hope you see the necessity
of it. OK,
so don't don't stop on the shallow
surface of the how it works.
Think in terms of the semantics if we are
not able to extend the value if we
deallocate.
The N variable when we exit the counter
function the the code will be broken
because when you execute this instance of
C1 there is no N variable. Sorry broken.
At the same time,
because when you call multiple time a
function, technically you activate you.
You have to allocate all the local
variables of that function because you
need them.
We have imposed to the PROGRAMMING
language runtime to keep alive a location
beyond the scope, the lexical scope,
because that variable has been captured.
OK, it's like a trap. It's being captured.
So at the first activation we know that
we allocate.
Local variable for M and.
And.
Add the second activation.
In this and basically all the programming
language modern programming languages,
you will have another N variable
allocated different from the previous one,
and for this reason the 1st result will
be bound to the first.
First instance of then the second the.
Execution will be bound to the second
activation event.
2.
What is?
A callable piece of code that whenever
you call it,
it may gives you a different result.
Depending on variables.
That are behind that, that, that, that.
That that you don't see.
I mean I here I invoke a counter and I
invoke the result and I get some behavior.
Then I invoke again count and I get a
different behavior.
This is typically an object.
OK,
because basically you have the function
which is the method and at this value
which is the state of the object.
So whenever I call counter,
I'm getting basically a very dumb object
with an integer as a field.
And a single method which is the the the
the return function.
Notice that if this was JavaScript I
could I could have also have written
increment.
Function.
And oops.
And I also could have written decrement
function.
And now I did return not one,
not two functions that refer the very
same N object.
So now if I write C dot inc I will get.
Uh, 0 if I type in.
C1 dot Inc I will got one get one and if
I type in C1 dot deck I will get 01.
Sorry you're right.
Deck.
It's the very.
So you're right.
That's correct. You you are,
you are former. That's good thing, OK.
So as you can see,
lexical closure can be used to have a
some form of object oriented PROGRAMMING
because basically they allow to secretly
bind.
A common state to multiple functions.
So this common state will be the state of
the object and the multiple function that
I share in this state are basically the
methods. That is the reason because.net.
Said OK if I need if I have a delegate.
Int OP int int this is this will be in C#
the the declaration.
So OP is the definition of a type.
I delegate now if I have a a class M with
the method.
And add.
In the int, let me simplify.
The syntax otherwise will be long.
Now I can say OO equal.
Oh, sorry, var M is new M.
And then I can say always a type OP equal
M dot add.
This is a very a valid program and if I
invoke.
That will invoke the add method OK and.
This particular syntax that have been
that has been introduced by C# more than
20 years ago was basically the need to be
able to have something that can be used.
For obtaining the same behavior.
Of the lexical closure that here I
presented in in the form of JavaScript.
And then C# originally just introduced
the type.
So as a programmer I use it to define
delegates, etcetera. C#, I don't know,
three or some subsequent.
The evolution of the language at some
point started to give me the syntax that
basically compiled down into that.
Basic object that is the delegate,
so moral of the story.
Lexical closures are.
One of many implication of the scoping
rules of a PROGRAMMING language.
So whenever you decide to support some
syntax in the PROGRAMMING language,
you are always have to consider that you
have to pay a price for that because the
we we are learning that PROGRAMMING
languages are deeply composable.
Because of the three induced by the
grammar and this way of composition as
implication also in the semantics and the
execution implementation of the language
in fact.
When I started introducing this WAP,
I made a statement which was partially
true.
I said no one impose me to have to
allocate this variable temp when I enter
the swoop and the allocate when I exit I
can allocate the TMP variable.
Statically all the time.
This is true for all the PROGRAMMING
languages that don't support recursion.
Because uh, if you have repulsion.
Then you have multiple activation of the
same function. I don't know.
Factor factorial of N is.
If N is equal one, then one else.
And and I'm so ******. Yeah,
my one should be OK.
So if I support.
But.
In the scoping rules,
I say that if I declare a function whose
name is fact,
that name is visible inside its
definition then.
The implication is that I'm allowed to
have recursive execution if I forbid this
in the grammar.
Then the language will not allow
recursion.
Then I can allocate statically all the
local variable of all the function and
simply reuse the slot anytime I I will be
called OK.
So I hope by now you see all these small
elements that are induced by the scoping
rule of the language.
So I invite you to not consider as your
colleague say static is because I it's
true. I mean the definition is correct.
Static is because.
Because when I read the name,
I know how to find the related
declaration and so I know which is the
value I'm referring to.
But that is only a very small part of a
long story,
because when you design A programming
language, the scoping rule will.
Define its implementation.
You want an example?
My and Andreas Favori PROGRAMMING
language Python until version 3.
Supported the syntax of lexical closure,
but actually they behaved wrong and the
scoping of the of the.
The scoping of the language was defined
by a rule that was called.
LGB rule, local,
global and the BI don't remember anymore
was this stand for,
which is basically the algorithm used by
the interpreter to scavenge the memory
and find the names OK.
OK.
So before introduce introducing the
consequence,
the probably the biggest consequence of
scoping and grammars, I would like to.
Introduce you the OR reintroduce you a
nice example of a PROGRAMMING language
that is almost statically scoped,
but there is a one notable exception and
you perhaps all know this language and
it's called JavaScript.
JavaScript is almost all statically typed
as scoped language. Sorry,
with one notable exception with there is
a specific variable which actually has a
fixed name in the definition,
but it's a variable.
And the name is this.
This is not a keyword,
is a name in the language,
and it has a very specific semantics that
is used in the language to provide the
illusion that you had objects. OK, so.
In JavaScript, whenever you write,
so let's define an object.
I'm using the jazz notation,
which is a little way to create an object.
OK, so.
Let's say ink.
Function and.
Return M + 1.
Imagine also the deck.
Should be quick enough.
Deck and and -1. That's it now.
If I type in a dot Inc,
we all know that I will get the print out
of the function.
JavaScript is interpreted as a language,
so the interpreter has the full
definition so it can print out.
The definition of the function.
If I invoke it, I will get 3.
That's it. That's easy.
Now there is some magic that happens when
I use a dot because the runtime.
Transform this invocation in first.
So whenever the language sees a dot
something, um.
There will be these equal a.
And then the function a docs dot X will
be invoked OK.
O.
At white.
JavaScript do this for one reason.
So suppose I have a.
Function.
Stack.
Oh.
Let's simplify my life, so.
I can write this name equal null this ID
equal Z -1. I don't know right?
So this is a a function in JavaScript.
Since the very beginning we're talking
about 967.
You can write also.
Var S new student.
This convinced all the JavaScript
programmers that Java JavaScript had
objects because there is a new,
so you must have objects,
which is not the case technically when
you write in this.
You have in reality this code executed as
gets in initialized with an empty object
because objects in JavaScript are
dictionaries, so no.
No keys.
Then this is equal to S and then student
gets invoked. OK,
so when you invoke student,
this will be bound to the empty object
and will populate the name.
Therefore in JavaScript you have static
scoping but for the this keyword.
And in fact,
when you start writing complicated
JavaScript code,
sometimes you you bump into some problem
because of the disk keyword then
JavaScript devote. Fortunately,
now it's considering mostly.
Functional language.
The object oriented the flavor given by
the syntax has been almost forgotten and
so we we're living in a much better world
when writing Java.
JavaScript programs,
but this is a good example of a very
twist in the scoping rules that it's
still there and you have to understand
when you want to understand a complicated.
JavaScript rogram.
As a weakness of this,
you can go and have some fun.
With an open source project of University
of Pisa that yesterday I just use it to
elect the rector of the University of
Calabria,
which is called the Legere that you
perhaps.
Already used that you can.
You're invited to browse the code.
I'm I'm the author,
so you can ask me in general.
I have answer to your questions and.
And if you browse and go.
To the code that that generates the
election card where you select the
candidates,
you will find very interesting.
And.
Complicated JavaScript patterns.
So if you want an example and this is so
complicated that even though I wrote this
code anytime I have to touch these.
I'm not feeling really confident that I
will not break something in this code. OK,
so if you want some example of some
treaty JavaScript code,
this can be one of many.
I could have picked it up by many.
Yesterday I spent some time reading this
code, so I it's in top of my mind. OK,
so last 10 minutes as in any class that
is respected.
Let's talk start talking about.
One of the largest implication of the
scoping rules supporting the memory
allocation.
So the the memory of a program we know is
always the memory of the program.
Leave it limited. Yeah, in please.
In future when we will have Turing
machine will be not.
For the moment we will accept this
limitation. It is limited and.
How is?
I mean how if we don't think that the
PROGRAMMING language in itself in the
process, the memory, how is?
Linear. It's a very long.
We know from operating system that this
very long sequence of cells that are
addressed linearly.
Technically are part of a virtual memory
and this has some implications in terms
of implementation,
but we live in this beautiful world that
a process has memory that goes from zero
to, I don't know, terabytes, 64 terabytes,
OK.
Um.
And that is very annoying to manage.
Because.
At the end of the day,
you have to decide of these billions
memory cells,
which values go where and whenever the
programmer has to access the value.
You need the address of the of the
location. OK so.
Long story short,
because you already know the the
conclusion, so it's not a spoiler.
Uh.
Thanks to Rikushan. Thanks to Rikushan.
We found that if we allocate,
if we reserve a portion of this linear
memory to a data structure that we all
know that is called the stack.
Then I can allocate local variables on
top of this stack,
use them and when you exit from the
function,
unless you support lexical closures,
in that case things complicate.
You can deallocate the top of the stack,
return the value and that's it.
So stack is a very nice data structure
because follows the functional view of a
PROGRAMMING language because basically we
like to invoke function because we like
mathematics.
And the way function gets invoked tend to
generate these push, pop, push,
pop of local variables.
And so why don't your PROGRAMMING
language supports you instead of having
you to explicitly manage this?
Very long stream of values.
You have the stack data structure
generated for you by the compiler O
behind the execution of.
Any PROGRAMMING language,
modern PROGRAMMING language,
there is not anymore the jump to the
subroutine as I did in the whitespace
compiler,
but there is a function invocation which
means.
Allocate variables on top of a stack,
execute the function which will use these
variables, deallocate, go back.
Nice because.
I can also ensure that.
I didn't use it today.
Let's use it.
Can you generate a diagram of a stack of
a PROGRAMMING PROGRAMMING language with
activation?
Records, records.
4.
Execution.
Let me see if I get a nice diagram.
So basically.
There is a name for the bunch of
variables,
few other things that gets loaded on top
of a stack that is called the activation
record. So whenever the compiler find.
Yeah.
That is basically the idea.
So in this picture it looks that the
stack grows downwards.
I would have picked it the other way
around, but nevertheless it's correct.
Technically in memory it will be
allocated like this if zero is on top so.
It makes sense. So as you can see,
every time you enter in a function,
you get some code generated by the
compiler for you,
which allocates the activation record.
So on top of the stack,
it allocates a few information that are.
Essential for executing the function.
These informations include the local
variables.
Return address is another interesting
part of the activation record.
So uh.
When you call the factorial of four then
you have the formal argument is bound to
actual to the value of four. OK,
so in the activation record there are no
on not only.
The local variables,
but also the formal parameters of the
function because you can assign them,
so you need some memory.
And.
Oh, yes. Thank you for the.
Much better. Sorry.
So this is a factor of int 4 is the
definition, so someone invokes fact 4.
And so you remember, OK,
when I when I finish executing the fact
function, I should go back to the caller.
So that is something that will change it
depending on the execution.
So that is part of the activation record.
Then.
Argument is for T.
Which is this local variable is waiting
for the value of factor of N -1,
so the actual value of T unknown waiting.
Factory actually is invoked another
activation record saying values T waiting.
Paman is 321.
One, we return one and so you pop.
So this way of laying out things,
it also allows us to implement scope
rules.
Because basically.
The I I see the base of the execution is
this frame and so there's no way for the
program for for the last function to
access the variables that lies on top of
the stack below on the stack.
That are of other functions. OK,
so the stack has also this beautiful
property that allows you to mask the rest
of the activation,
so you have no clue about who called you.
And what are the values of the local
variables?
Because this stack naturally hides the
previous calls. OK,
so you see how the scoping rules and the
implementation that they tend to induce.
Interwine with the actual execution of
the of the code.
We will see later on that there are even
more pretty stuff.
I mean this is not yet at the moment, so.
Very long string of bytes to the memory
of a processor.
The scoping induce the automatic
management of the memory.
Unfortunately that is not enough.
It will be very nice to be able to write
programs that only need local variables,
but unfortunately this is not the case as
you wait.
You will know.
So we also have static memory,
but that that's easy memory that gets
allocated when the program is loaded and
it stays there for till the end of the
execution of the program and dynamic
memory which is.
All the rest of the memory that you need
that to allocate at some point and you
don't want.
That that part of a memory gets
deallocated at the exit of a function.
I'm pretty sure you're familiar with the
new keyword,
which is the traditional now keyword to
introduce the allocation and.
Memory management is one of the main
issue of rogramming because.
If you don't deallocate memory,
you waste the memory.
The process will exhaust the memory,
the system will misbehave.
Um.
You may deallocate,
so you may reuse a portion of a memory
for something else before.
The time and in that case you will get a
dangling pointer.
So the address of a location where you
assume there is some value,
but in fact there is not and typically
that leads to a crash of or or some
misbehave.
Of the of the program.
So all these conditions led to very,
very harsh fights in the strategies of
memory management.
So we will start investigating.
A few strategies.
The one is the the C way you allocate
explicitly memory location and you're
free explicitly is up to you.
Even in the 70s there was a struggle
between C programming.
They say memory is too important to let
the system manage.
The programmer knows better and the least
programmer that says memory is too
important to let the system to let the
programmer manage it.
Let's leave it to the system, OK?
40 years later, least PROGRAMMING won.
Basically most of the code is written
today is with systems that automatically
manage memory, so explicit management.
Is 1 approach.
Of course it's more efficient because you
you as a programmer should know when the
memory is needed and when you can free it.
And if you're a perfect programmer
everything will be better.
But unfortunately this is not the case.
Then there is a simple form that is
called reference counting that we will
explore, which is a sort of way to.
To keep track of semi automatically of
the how many are still interested in that
particular variable.
Then there is the garbage collection
which is behind java.net JavaScript and.
TypeScript, blah blah blah,
pretty much everything.
And then there is Rust.
Rust is interesting because it tried to.
It tried to discipline the explicit
management of the memory so that you
don't give up to the efficiency that you
get.
By memory, explicit memory management,
but by reducing human error in
implementing that and it's considered,
I will say a unicum in in its in its way
and so.
It is worth having few words about that.
OK. So I think we're done for today.
Thank you. See you tomorrow.